<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine rules for Christian unity opened and urged a sermon / preach'd in the Cathedral Church of Norwich, October 16, 1692 by Erasmus Warren, rector of Worlington in Suffolk.</title>
            <author>Warren, Erasmus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28908</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10776105</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10776105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45821</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67684)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45821)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1412:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine rules for Christian unity opened and urged a sermon / preach'd in the Cathedral Church of Norwich, October 16, 1692 by Erasmus Warren, rector of Worlington in Suffolk.</title>
                  <author>Warren, Erasmus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Oliver, and are to be sold by J. Robinson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian union --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45821:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45821:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Divine Rules for Chriſtian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity Opened and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd in the <hi>Cathedral Church</hi> OF NORWICH, <hi>October</hi> 16. 1692.</p>
            <p>By ERASMUS WARREN, Rector of <hi>Worlington</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Be of one Mind, <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 13.11.</hi>
               </bibl> If there be therefore any Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in <hi>CHRIST;</hi> if any Comfort of Love; if any Fellowſhip of the <hi>SPIRIT;</hi> if any Bowels and Mercies; fulfil ye my joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind, <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 2.1, 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Oliver</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Norwich,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>J. Robinſon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:45821:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45821:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful <hi>MICHAEL BEVERLY</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> MAYOR OF THE City of NORWICH.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT was St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Complaint long ſince (and a very ſad one, becauſe a very true one)<note n="*" place="margin">Videns ille idola dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licta, &amp; per nimium creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium populum ſedes ſuas ac templa deſerta, excogitave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit novam fraudem, ut ſub ipſo Chriſtiani nominis titulo fallat incautos. Haereſes inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit &amp; Schiſmata, quibus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verteret fidem, veritatem cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumperet, ſcinderet <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitatem. De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit. Eccle.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>the Devil ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Idols left, and his Seats and Temples forſaken by a Multitude of Believing People, thought of a new Cheat, how under the very Title of the Chriſtian Name, he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Unwary. He invented Hereſies and Schiſms, whereby he might ſubvert the Faith, corrupt the Truth, and cut UNITY aſunder.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45821:3"/> And how very ſucceſsful this Invention of his has been, and how many and grievous Miſchiefs it has wrought, and may ſtill produce, Experience ſhews us, and gives us but too good Grounds to ſuſpect. I pray GOD make us throughly ſenſible of it, and ſo deeply affect every one of us with it; as that the Dangers which threaten us, and grow upon us from our unhappy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, may be timely prevented, and for ever ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeded, by a ſpeedy and perfect Cloſure of all ſides. And O what a Bleſſed Change would it be (conſidering how we are crumbled into Sects and Factions) to have our many Differences moulded up into one common Intereſt; and all ſeparate Parties melted down into Chriſtian Unity!</p>
            <p>Might this Diſcourſe in the leaſt Meaſure contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to that Glorious Work, I ſhould never repent of its Publication, though I was drawn to it with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, Sir, when I outſtood your firſt Motions to it, and thoſe that were made by other excellent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, while I was in your City; I hoped and concluded that I had finally freed my ſelf from farther Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of that nature. But when I found that they followed me into the Country, and when I met with this Paſſage, amongſt others, in your Letter, <hi>It is not only my Opinion, that your Sermon will be Serviceable to the Publick, towards Healing the
<pb facs="tcp:45821:3"/> Breaches that are amongſt us; but others of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Judgment than my ſelf, do unanimouſly agree to the ſame; and all People that I converſe with, deſire that I would uſe my Intereſt, to perſwade you to Print it.</hi> I then thought I had reaſon to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and accordingly have done it.</p>
            <p>And truly fear of Cenſure, as well as force of Intreaty, prevailed with me to gratifie you in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. For in caſe I had refuſed, they who deſired the Sermon might come abroad, would have condemn'd me, it may be, for not duly practiſing my own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, which preſs'd Men by all the means they could uſe, to endeavour Unity: <hi>Than which</hi> (you both wiſely and ſeriouſly note in your Letter aforeſaid) <hi>as nothing can be more ſeaſonably diſcourſed on; ſo there is not any thing more deſirable by good Chriſtians, or more to be ſought after in this divided Nation.</hi> I heartily wiſh that <hi>All</hi> were of your Mind, then it might be hoped that their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours after Spiritual Unity, would be ſuch, as GOD would Bleſs with Happy Succeſs. At leaſt, Sir, it would make People very careful to omit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing conducive thereunto, if I may judge by your Procedure. For not ſo much as <hi>One</hi> ſingle Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, tending to Union, could be heard by you; but as mean as it is, you would have it made publick. In caſe it proves Inſtrumental that way, I ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:45821:4"/> greatly rejoyce in my compliance with you. And if it does not, I ſhall ſtill have the Satisfaction of anſwering the Deſires of many Good Men; and more particularly of teſtifying my ſelf to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Humble Servant,</hi> E. Warren.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45821:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Epheſians 4.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Endeavouring to keep the Unity of the SPIRIT in the Bond of Peace.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>A Moſt Kind and Important Petition was that which our adorable LORD in the Days of his Fleſh, put up for his Proſelytes, St. <hi>John</hi> 17.21. <hi>That they all may be one, as Thou, Father, art in me, and I in Thee; that they alſo may be one in us.</hi> O that the GOD who heareth Prayers, would pleaſe to anſwer it in the Fullneſs of it!</p>
            <p>But that ſo great a Bleſſing may come down exuberant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the Body of Chriſtians, and continue with them; ſomething muſt be done on their part: That is, the Unity their LORD prayed for, they muſt labour after.</p>
            <p>It is ſtiled <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the</hi> SPIRIT, becauſe as it joyns us together in <hi>one Mind</hi> or <hi>Spirit;</hi> ſo it is wrought by the Efficiency or Operation of the HOLY GHOST.</p>
            <p>It may be thus deſcribed: It is <hi>a Bleſſed Agreement of Spiritual Perſons, in Spiritual Matters, to Spiritual Ends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An AGREEMENT: For even in Natural as well as amongſt Rational Beings, there can be no Union where there is no Concord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Agreement</hi> of SPIRITUAL PERSONS: That is, of CHRISTIANS: Who, though in their Natural Capacity they are like other Men; yet in their Religious Profeſſion they are diſtinguiſh'd from them, it being <hi>Spiritual</hi> in all regards. For the Author of it is Spiritual, CHRIST: The Rule of it is Spiritual, the Goſpel: The Inſtruments of it are Spiritual Ordinances: The Exerciſe of it is in Spiritual Duties: The Ends of it are Spiritual Excellencies: The
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45821:5"/> Motives to it are Spiritual Inducements: The Rewards of it are Spiritual Attainments: The very Confederacy in it is by Spiritual Ligaments: Whether we conſider Chriſtians as tied together in a Community amongſt themſelves; or as a Myſtical Body joyned to their Sovereign Head. So that <hi>Infidels</hi> agreeing never ſo well, muſt be wide of this Unity of the SPIRIT: At beſt they can make but a <hi>Political</hi> or <hi>Superſtitious Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Agreement in Spiritual</hi> MATTERS: As in <hi>Doctrin, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, Liturgy, Government:</hi> So that let Chriſtians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves agree never ſo fully as to Secular Affairs, they would be much below the Unity of the SPIRIT: Their Agreement would riſe no higher than a <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Amicable</hi> Combination.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To Spiritual</hi> ENDS: As to the Honour of GOD, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of His Kingdom, the Good and Happineſs of the Souls of Men: So that ſhould Chriſtians agree never ſo throughly in Spiritual Matters to <hi>Temporal</hi> Ends, they would be ſhort of the Unity of the SPIRIT ſtill. For their Ends muſt either be <hi>Innocent</hi> or <hi>Sinful.</hi> If <hi>Innocent,</hi> they would be but a <hi>Selfiſh</hi> Aſſociation: If <hi>Sinful,</hi> an <hi>Impious</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful</hi> one.</p>
            <p>And therefore laſtly, it is a BLESSED <hi>Agreement;</hi> and that in ſeveral Reſpects: In reſpect of its <hi>Origin,</hi> as ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Bleſſed Principles: In reſpect of its <hi>Influence,</hi> as producing Bleſſed Effects: In reſpect of its <hi>Tendency</hi> and <hi>Subſervience,</hi> as promoting our preſent, and miniſtring to our future endleſs Beatitude. And thus it is diſtinguiſh'd from all other Agreements upon Earth.</p>
            <p>Now to preſerve and promote this Spiritual Unity, I ſhall humbly offer ſome plain <hi>Rules</hi> or <hi>Directions.</hi> Six of them ſhall be taken out of the Context, and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they muſt be of the more Weight, and I hope will be of the more Efficacy. They are theſe:
<list>
                  <item>1ſt. Be ſenſible of the great need of Unity.</item>
                  <item>2ly. Learn to be deeply Humble.</item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45821:5"/>
                  <item>3ly. Labour for a meek Temper of Mind.</item>
                  <item>4ly. Arm your ſelves with Long-ſuffering.</item>
                  <item>5ly. Exerciſe mutual Forbearance.</item>
                  <item>6ly. Live in Chriſtian Love.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>They are all couched in the two firſt Verſes of the Chapter: <hi>I beſeech you that ye walk worthy of the Vocation wherewith ye are called; with all Lowlineſs and Meekneſs, with Long-ſuffering, Forbearing one another in Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Be ſenſible of the great need of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity:</hi> It is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary upon the Account of our <hi>Calling:</hi> Of our high, holy, Heavenly Calling; as it is denominated in the Sacred Volume. And therefore that we might go the right way to work, and be inclin'd to endeavour it from a juſt Senſe of the Neceſſity of it; the Apoſtle directs us, in the firſt place, to walk <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>worthy of the Vocation wherewith we are called:</hi> Intimating we can never do that, never be worthy Diſciples of CHRIST, without Unity.</p>
            <p>For impoſſible it is that any ſhould walk worthy of their Calling, whatever it be, unleſs they anſwer the Nature of it, and advance it. But there is no doing either of theſe, as to our Chriſtian Vocation, without Unity.</p>
            <p>Without Unity we cannot <hi>anſwer the Nature of our Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> And the Reaſon is evident, becauſe a main part of that Vocation is Unity; As GOD has called us to Peace, and called us to Holineſs, and called us to His Kingdom, as the Divine Oracles teſtifie: So he has called us to Unity, as much as to any thing, as appears there.</p>
            <p>Nor muſt we forget that the Holy JESUS honoured Chriſtians with many excellent and noble Gifts, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with <hi>glorious</hi> or <hi>miraculous</hi> ones, on purpoſe to bring them into Unity, and keep them in it. <hi>The <hi>Glory</hi> which Thou gaveſt me, I have given them:</hi> And why? <hi>That they may be <hi>one,</hi> even as we are one,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> 17.22.</p>
            <p>Yea, the great things of our Religion, (not to ſay the whole of it) ſeem to be deſign'd to this End; to indear us
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45821:6"/> mightily and cloſely to unite us. The very Genius of it leads that way directly, and invites and draws moſt powerfully to it: For ſays St. <hi>Paul,</hi> juſt after the Text, <hi>There is one Body, and one</hi> SPIRIT, <hi>even as ye are called in one Hope of your Calling; one</hi> LORD, <hi>one Faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, one</hi> GOD <hi>and Father of all.</hi> Such a Divine <hi>Sorites</hi> or heap of Arguments perſwading to Unity, as can no where be parallell'd. Were Chriſtians incorporate in different Bodies; or were the one Body in which they are incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, animated by different Spirits; or did the one SPIRIT which animates them, allot them different Callings; or did the one Calling allotted them, allow them different Hopes; or did the one Hope allowed them, tye them to different LORDS; or did the one LORD they are obliged to, give them different Faiths; or to the one Faith given them, were they admitted by different Baptiſms; or in their one initiating Baptiſm, were they devoted to different GODS; or were the one GOD, to whom they are devoted, not their Father; they might then be divided, and could not well help it. Yea, Diviſion, which is now their Sin, might then be their Duty. But the Caſe is nothing ſo. On the contrary, there is but one Body, that is, the Church into which true Chriſtians are grafted: But one SPIRIT, the HOLY GHOST, by which they are illivened: But one Calling, the Evangelical Religion in which they are engaged: But one Hope, that of Salvation, by which they are encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged: But one LORD, that is, CHRIST, by whom they are redeemed: But one Faith, that is, of the Goſpel, which by them is profeſſed: But one Baptiſm, that is, of JESUS, by which they are conſecrated: But one GOD, that is, the living and true GOD, by whom they were created, are governed, and ſhall be preſerved; and this GOD is their Father too, and therefore they muſt all be nearly related. So that here is ſuch a number of Motives to Unity, and of ſtrong Obligations binding to it, that <hi>none</hi> more <hi>need,</hi> and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45821:6"/> 
               <hi>few</hi> more <hi>can</hi> be added of the ſame Nature. Were they rightly conſidered, how is it poſſible that Chriſtians ſhould divide? When in ſo doing, or ſuffering it to be done, they muſt break the Frame or Contexture of their Religion, and go againſt the Temper and Conſtitution of it, and fail moſt ſhamefully in their proper <hi>Vocation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If at any time therefore, or upon any occaſion, we grow too hot, and our Minds ferment, and our Paſſions boil, ſo as to threaten any thing of Diviſion, let us but take our Bibles in our Hands, and deliberately read, and ſeriouſly ruminate on this Paragraph, and ſurely it will be enough to cool that Heat, and quench that Fire, which would inflame us to Diſſention. Let me ask, are we willing to unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian our ſelves? Why, if we do not endeavour to keep Unity, we take too great a ſtep towards it: At leaſt we fall very ſhort of our <hi>Calling,</hi> and whatever Figures we ſeem to make, in a great meaſure we are no better than Cyphers: Chriſtians without Unity, and without endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to keep it, are ſomewhat like Scholars without Learning, and without ſtudying to get it: They want an Eſſential of their Profeſſion, or a moſt neceſſary Piece of it; nor do they take due care to attain unto it and be accompliſh'd in it.</p>
            <p>And as we cannot anſwer the <hi>Nature</hi> of our Calling without Unity, ſo neither can we <hi>advance</hi> it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when our LORD prayed for his Diſciples (as we noted at firſt) that they <hi>all might be one,</hi> He gives this Reaſon why He ſued for their Unity, <hi>That the World might believe that Thou hast ſent me:</hi> So that Unity in the Church of GOD, is to propagate Faith in the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> or Son of GOD, and to advance Chriſtianity in the World: And is it not highly needful then, and does it not behove us to endeavour to keep it amongſt our ſelves, and to promote it ſo far as we can with others?</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45821:7"/>
            <p>Our Bleſſed LORD taught us to Pray (and I hope we do it every day more than once) that His <hi>Kingdom may come;</hi> That His Heavenly Religion may grow great and powerful, and rule in the Hearts and Lives of Men; That it may take deep root in all places, and yield much Fruit; That it may thrive and flouriſh more than ever it did, aſcending to the higheſt Pitch, and ſpreading to the wideſt Latitude. But when we pray thus, if we do not endeavour to keep Unity, like egregious Diſſemblers we not only fruſtrate our own Devotions; but to GOD's Diſhonour, and the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of our ſelves and others, ſet back the Bleſſing for which we ſupplicate.</p>
            <p>It is the Judgment of Learned and Pious Men, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the End of the World, there ſhall be an happy Change in it: The Jews ſhall be converted, the Gentiles more fully called, and true Chriſtianity greatly exalted. Now would it not be huge Satisfaction to us, to have this Glorious Elevation of Religion come to paſs in <hi>our days?</hi> Why then let all unfeigned Servants of JESUS do what in them lyes to haſten it: And amongſt other things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive thereunto, let them endeavour to keep the Unity of the SPIRIT: So we ſhall ſee Religion riſe, and help it to culminate or advance apace to its wiſhed Heighth. And when once it gets into its <hi>Zenith</hi> in the Church, and ſhines forth in its full Strength and Luſtre, who knows what an Influence it may have far and near, and how much of the World may be taken Captive with the Charming Beauty and Glories of it? Whereas Diviſions do naturally throw Contempt on Chriſtianity, and grievouſly diminiſh and eclipſe it; for it makes ſtrangers to it apt to ſuſpect, that it is too weak to carry on its own Deſigns, whereof Unity is one: Or elſe that its Profeſſors (who are fitteſt to judge) have no great opinion of its worth, and therefore ſlight it in one of the grand Neceſſaries of it: And when they who are unacquainted with our Religion, or have little eſteem
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45821:7"/> and love for the ſame, have occaſion given them to take ſuch crooked Meaſures of it; no wonder if they be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced and ſet againſt it, and ſo its Propagation be check'd and hindred.</p>
            <p>Upon this account, in the firſt place, let us zealouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keep the Unity of the SPIRIT; elſe we plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare, that we have no <hi>thorough Senſe</hi> of the <hi>Nature</hi> of our <hi>Calling,</hi> and no <hi>juſt Concern</hi> to <hi>advance</hi> it as we ought; and ſo neither <hi>do,</hi> nor <hi>can</hi> walk worthy of it: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorting Chriſtians to a Converſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the Goſpel, which is the ſame thing as to walk worthy of their Vocation; adviſeth them to <hi>ſtand fast in <hi>one</hi> Spirit, with <hi>one</hi> Mind,</hi> Phil. 1.27. That for the firſt Rule.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Learn to be deeply Humble:</hi> Pride in a Society, is like Motion in Matter, which naturally works a Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Parts, and the Diſſolution of Continuity; and is able to turn the hardeſt Rock into volatile or fluid Atoms. But Humility, on the other ſide, is like Reſt, which unites and Conſolidates. And therefore to preſerve Unity, the Apoſtle will have us, in the ſecond place, to walk <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>with all Lowlineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pride makes Men conceited; and Self-conceit makes them ſingular; and Singularity makes them differ from others; and Difference from others (be it in Opinion or Practice) breeds Diſſention; and Diſſention ſhatters Unity.</p>
            <p>Pride makes Men Moroſe; and Moroſeneſs makes them Peeviſh; and Peeviſhneſs makes them Captious and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous; and captious Humorſomneſs hinders Compliance in requiſite things; and Non-compliance hinders Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; and Non-conformity diſturbs Unity.</p>
            <p>Pride makes Men Heady; and Headineſs makes them Unruly; and Unrulineſs makes them Diſorderly; and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderlineſs makes them Diſobedient; and Diſobedience disjoynts Unity.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45821:8"/>
            <p>Pride makes Men Contentious; it is the <hi>ſole</hi> or <hi>chief</hi> cauſe of their being ſo: <hi>Only <hi>by Pride cometh Contention,</hi>
               </hi> Prov. 13.10. And Contention begets Diviſion; and Diviſion is an actual Breach of Unity.</p>
            <p>Pride makes Men Ambitious; and Ambition makes them Furious in driving to what they aim at: And when their Fury is up, and they are hot in their Chaſe, they care not through what they run, ſo they attain their End. If <hi>Hereſie</hi> or <hi>Schiſm, Sedition</hi> or <hi>Rebellion,</hi> lye in their way, they matter not ruſhing into any of them, perhaps not plunging into all. But then Unity is ſure to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown and trampled on.</p>
            <p>Nor are particular Churches only thus rent to pieces by Pride, but alſo the Church Univerſal is filled with Schiſms. For what is it that makes one Church <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp</hi> upon another; that ſets one Church to <hi>Domineer</hi> over another; that cauſes one Church to <hi>Excommunicate</hi> and <hi>Anathematize</hi> another, whereby Catholick Unity is deſtroyed, but Pride chiefly?</p>
            <p>As we prize and love Unity therefore, let us down with Pride, and reſolve to walk humbly with GOD and all Men; towards our Betters, Equals and Inferiors; towards them that are our Friends, and them that are our Enemies; towards them that agree with us, and them that diſſent from us; let us walk with <hi>Lowlineſs:</hi> If <hi>they</hi> be haughty and inſolent towards <hi>us,</hi> let <hi>us,</hi> for ineſtimable Unity's ſake, demean our ſelves with <hi>all <hi>Lowlineſs</hi>
               </hi> towards them.</p>
            <p>And why ſhould we not? For Lord! What have we to be proud of? Are we not Frailty and Duſt, and ſo Nothing? Are we not Corruption and Sin, and ſo worſe than nothing? And for ſuch Nothings, and worſe than Nothings as we, to ſwell with Pride, would be Folly and Sin enough, though the Poyſon of it wrought only <hi>within</hi> us. But when its Venom is ſpreading and diffuſive, and breaths out a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion fatal to Unity; not to throw off Pride and put on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45821:8"/> Humility, muſt be ſinful Folly of a larger ſize, and GOD forbid we ſhould be guilty of it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Labour for a meek Temper of Mind:</hi> As the Wiſe Man aſſures us, <hi>Wrath is Cruel, and Anger is Outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,</hi> Prov. 27.4. And truly ſo Cruel is <hi>Wrath,</hi> that it will kill Unity, where it is not reſtrained. And as <hi>Solomon</hi> there expreſſes it, ſuch a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>outragious Inundation</hi> is <hi>Anger,</hi> that if it be not kept within Bounds, it will not fail to overflow and drown it. And therefore to preſerve Unity, the Apoſtle urges us, in the third place, to walk <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>with Meekneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anger, we know, is a ſhort Madneſs, as the Moraliſt teaches: And where it Tumultuates and Rages, it even degrades Humanity, and makes Men to act in ways un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of themſelves: It diſtracts the Mind, and roils the Spirit, and throws it into wild and ruful Diſorders. It puts down the uſe of Judgment for the time, and exalts Phrenſie into the Throne of Reaſon: It quite overthrows Wiſdom's Empire; and putting the Scepter into Folly's hand, ſets it up to domineer in all our Capacities. For then it is, to uſe <hi>Philo</hi>'s Diſtinction, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Feminine Part</hi> of us, prevails againſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Maſculine:</hi> That <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Child in us,</hi> according to <hi>Simplicius,</hi> is too hard for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the inner Man,</hi> as the Chriſtian Doctrin calls it: That <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Beast,</hi> according to <hi>Plotinus,</hi> vanquiſhes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the intellectual Power:</hi> That <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to the <hi>Stoicks, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs,</hi> bafles <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Mind:</hi> That <hi>Paſſions,</hi> which according to <hi>Maximus Tyrius,</hi> are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Populace,</hi> or <hi>Mob</hi> of the Soul; mutiny againſt and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the ruling Faculty.</hi> And ſo, to ſpeak in <hi>Lucian</hi>'s Language, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Lordly part of the Soul,</hi> which, he ſays, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Daemon given to every one,</hi> (and in <hi>Plato</hi>'s ſtile is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the GOD within us</hi>) and dwells <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the Top of the Body;</hi> is ſunk below its own Dignity, and indecently ſubjugated to baſe Extravagancies.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:45821:9"/>
            <p>So that if through want of Meekneſs we be habitually Wrathful, and ſubject to vehement Tranſports of Anger, we muſt needs be unfit to keep Unity, as being at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with our ſelves, and quite unhing'd and out of order, by reaſon of inteſtine Feuds and Jarrings: And they that have loſt the Government of <hi>themſelves,</hi> cannot but be deſtitute of that Gentleneſs and Moderation, and of that prudent Care and winning Conduct, which is neceſſary to preſerving Unity with <hi>others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then a cholerick ireful Temper untam'd, being ſo utterly inconſiſtent with Unity, and deſtructive to it, how ready ſhould we be to liſten to the Apoſtle, where he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth (in the laſt Verſe ſave one of this Chapter) <hi>Let <hi>all</hi> Wrath and Anger be put away.</hi> Let us quell thoſe fierce and bluſtering Storms, which are apt not only to blow up <hi>Autocracy</hi> by the Roots, but to ruffle <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> by ruining Self-government: And let us labour hard for a ſedate and calm, for a quiet and compoſed Frame of Mind; for ſo mild, and ſmooth, and meek a Temper, as may diſpoſe us to Unity, and fix us in it; as may glue us together in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Communion, and make us ſtick cloſe and faſt to each other, by a firm and inſeparable Spiritual Coheſion.</p>
            <p>But if we will not take the Holy Council given us, and curb our hot and turbulent Spirits, but will carry Gun-powder Paſſions about us, that are ready to take fire from every ſpark of Provocation which is ſtruck into them; no marvel if at laſt we be miſerably blown up, and broken and ſhattered all to pieces.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Arm your ſelves with Long-ſuffering.</hi> The three former Rules proved againſt <hi>our giving Offence</hi> to others; But Unity may as well be hindred or deſtroyed by <hi>taking the Offences</hi> which <hi>they</hi> give: And therefore to fortifie us againſt that, and ſo the better to ſecure Unity, the Apoſtle deſires us, in the Fourth place, to walk <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>with Long-ſuffering.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:45821:9"/>
            <p>We are infallibly aſſured that Offences will come; ſome of a lower and lighter, others of an higher and heavier Nature: Some ſingle and tranſient, others com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated and more permanent: Some through the Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſimple and unwary, others through the Willfulneſs of ill-meaning Men. Now <hi>our part</hi> it is to be <hi>roiled</hi> and <hi>provoked</hi> by <hi>none</hi> of theſe; but to <hi>ſuffer them all</hi> ſo far as we may, and as evenly as we can, for dear Unity's ſake.</p>
            <p>And ſo let us do: Let us <hi>be patient toward all Men,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.14. If any affront us, if any abuſe us, if any injure us, let us take all patiently; receiving their various Wrongs and Contumelies, juſt as a Feather-bed or Bank of Sand, do Stones thrown againſt them, without noiſe, or rebounding back upon thoſe that threw them.</p>
            <p>Not that Chriſtians are at any rate to become <hi>Stoicks.</hi> That's not only improper, but impoſſible; for they who are tenderly to ſimpathize with <hi>all,</hi> can never be ſenſeleſs in <hi>themſelves,</hi> nor poſſeſſed with dull Apathy as to their <hi>own</hi> Concerns. But let us ſo improve in the Grace of Long-ſuffering, as to be able generouſly to overlook In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities; and to ſtand under Injuries with ſo little un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſineſs and ill Reſentment, as that when we feel the <hi>worſt</hi> Harms which Men can do us, they may <hi>ſeem</hi> as if they were not done. <hi>Ye have not injured me at all,</hi> ſaid the great inſpired Doctor to the <hi>Galatians.</hi> And this he ſpake when they had aſperſed him with black and bitter Calumnies, and vehemently oppoſed both his Doctrin and Practice, and even queſtion'd his very Apoſtolical Commiſſion: Than which, what could go nearer to him?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Exerciſe mutual Forbearance. Bear ye one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Burdens,</hi> ſays the HOLY GHOST, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2. Though the <hi>Infirmities</hi> of People, or their <hi>Faults</hi> be ſuch, as to become an <hi>heavy Burthen</hi> to us; yet ſtill we are bound in many Caſes, and with much Patience, to bear with them. The <hi>laſt</hi> Rule intimates ſo much. But <hi>that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45821:10"/> Toleration</hi> or bearing with them, is not enough to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Unity, unleſs we go farther, and <hi>forbear</hi> them alſo. And therefore to this the Apoſtle leads us, in the fifth place, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Forbearing one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Forbearance muſt be expreſs'd in theſe five Inſtances at leaſt.</p>
            <p>Forbear
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Deſpiſing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cenſuring.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aggravating.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Reproaching.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Revenging.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Forbear <hi>Deſpiſing.</hi> Honour all Men, is the Divine Command; and therefore we can ſlight none ſcornfully and be blameleſs: Differ from Men we may, and in ſome things we muſt, but Deſpiſe them we may not: That's a Sin, and if we commit it, 'tis at our Peril.</p>
            <p>Thy way is ſtrait and even, and ſafe and pleaſant, and in it thou walkeſt ſmoothly on, while many unhappy Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers about thee do otherwiſe: Some of them ſlip, and ſome of them fall, and ſome of them wander they know not whither: But wilt thou deſpiſe them for this? Tell me firſt, Why art not thou of their unfortunate number? Perhaps thy Education was better, or thy Apprehenſion is quicker, or thy Judgment is ſounder. O think then who gave thee theſe Advantages, and be thankful to <hi>Him:</hi> And becauſe he hath denied the like to others, be not ſlighty but pitiful to <hi>them.</hi> If <hi>thine</hi> Eye-ſight be clearer than <hi>theirs,</hi> make good uſe of it; but by no means laugh at the Blind for loſing their way: <hi>They</hi> would be glad with all their Hearts, to have as <hi>good</hi> Eyes as <hi>thine</hi> in their Heads; and if they had them, might uſe them as <hi>well,</hi> it may be <hi>better</hi> than <hi>thou</hi> doſt. Pity them therefore in that they want; what, it may be, they are willing to have, and what it were better for them to enjoy.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:45821:10"/>
            <p>Should any leave ſuch a Church as this, wherein are all things Neceſſary and Decent, to worſhip GOD in a raw and wild kind of Room, we ſhould be apt to think them guilty of <hi>Weakneſs:</hi> And ſo we ſhould likewiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>them</hi> to be, who go out of ſuch a lightſom Church, into one more Gay and Splendid, but withall ſo dark, that in it they cannot ſee either to read the Scriptures, or to diſcern Bread from Fleſh, or to diſtinguiſh Wine from Blood. But then the more our Brethrens <hi>Weakneſs</hi> appears to <hi>us,</hi> the more Commiſeration we muſt ſhew to <hi>them:</hi> But if inſtead of Compaſſion we expreſs Scorn, <hi>we</hi> miſtake unhappily as well as <hi>they,</hi> and worſt <hi>our ſelves</hi> by evil <hi>Carriage,</hi> as they do <hi>themſelves</hi> by an evil <hi>Choice.</hi> And ſhall be ſo far from drawing them to Unity, that we ſhall rather drive them farther from it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Forbear Cenſuring.</hi> 'Tis good to have a piercing impartial Eye, but yet on many things we muſt look with connivence, and not only wink at, but exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate them: We are not to put Mens Actions upon the Tenters, and to ſtretch them to the worſt ſenſe they are capable of; if we do, we violate the Law of our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Religion, which lays an Obligation upon us to the contrary, <hi>Judge not.</hi> Nor are we bound from it in point of <hi>Religion</hi> only, but of <hi>Policy</hi> too; upon account of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,</hi> as well as of <hi>Duty. Judge not, that ye be not judged:</hi> Plainly intimating, that if we be <hi>ſevere,</hi> the Rigor we uſe we muſt expect, and that from GOD, as well as from <hi>Men.</hi> Let us therefore weigh <hi>others</hi> with Grains of Allowance, that ſo the ſame may be done to <hi>us.</hi> But if we carp Cenſoriouſly, and fling at <hi>them,</hi> ſhould GOD not be angry, <hi>Men</hi> will retaliate; and we need not queſtion but we ſhall meet with thoſe that will pay us ſufficiently in our <hi>own</hi> Coin.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:45821:11"/>
            <p>Though were nothing of this to enſue, we ought to be wonderful Cautious in Cenſuring, for <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>Miſtake,</hi> which we may <hi>eaſily</hi> run into: For there may be great difference betwixt what <hi>ſeems</hi> to be, and what really is. Judging <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>according to appearance,</hi> made our SAVIOUR once paſs for a <hi>Sabbath breaker,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> for a <hi>Setter-forth of Strange GODS.</hi> And through the ſame falſe Glaſs do <hi>they</hi> look, who in our neceſſary Rejection of dangerous Errors, and Separation from them, can deſcry Hereſie and damnable Apoſtaſie; and in our lawful uſeful Ceremonies, can ſee Antichriſtianiſm and groſs Idolatry. But that's the common Fault of raſh Cenſuring, to clap a moſt ugly Vizard of Guilt upon the Face of Innocence; and to beſmear Integrity with miſimputed Wickedneſs. In dread and Deteſtation of ſo foul an Enormity, let us Cenſure none but upon ſureſt Grounds.</p>
            <p>And truly where <hi>Actions</hi> deſerve to be cenſured, the <hi>Agents</hi> may <hi>ſometimes</hi> be very well ſpared: For where there is Darkneſs in the Mind, there may be Sincerity in the Soul; and invincible Ignorance will excuſe many Errors: It is one thing not to diſcern the Truth, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deny it, deſert it, detain it in Unrighteouſneſs: We are not preſently to count them <hi>deſperately</hi> Wicked, all whoſe Practices we cannot juſtifie: Heaven it ſelf looks not upon all as Factious and Idolatrous in their <hi>Hearts,</hi> who are ſo in their <hi>Ways,</hi> in their <hi>Worſhip:</hi> Let not us accuſe, where there is any good hope that GOD will approve; nor be forward to condemn, whom his Mercy may acquit. As many are much worſe than their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion can permit, ſo ſome are much better than their Principles do allow. Put the favourableſt Conſtruction therefore upon <hi>all</hi> Perſons and their Actions, and think as fairly of them as poſſibly you can, taking in all appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Circumſtances, and judging by the Rules of inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Candor: For I do not mean that any of us ſhould
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45821:11"/> call Black White at any rate. Where things are Evident and Notorious, we muſt ſee them in their own Colours, and not ſtick to call them by their proper Names. They who call Evil Good, and put Darkneſs for Light, are marked out by GOD Himſelf, in the fifth of <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> and we there find what Stamp they are of: To pronounce that naught which really is ſo, is no culpable Cenſure, but a commendable Judgment: And they who cannot or dare not paſs it, upon juſt occaſion, proclaim to the World, that they have little Underſtanding, or no great Uprightneſs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Forbear Aggravating. Epictetus</hi> ſays every thing has <hi>two</hi> Handles: And if ſo, Ingenuity (to mention nothing higher) ſhould teach us never to take hold of the <hi>worſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where there are no Faults, be ſure to make none: Where there are but little ones, make them not great: Where there are great ones, make them not bigger than they are.</p>
            <p>Too many go the contrary way, and are violent in it: They love to raiſe Mountains out of Mole-hills, and to blow up harmleſs Shadows into hideous Monſters: What is ſpoken in height of Fanſie, they draw down to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe: And what paſſes in heat of Paſſion or Diſpute, they interpret to be Mens ſettled Judgments: What they find amiſs in the Speeches, Writings and Carriages of <hi>ſome,</hi> they impute to <hi>all</hi> of the <hi>ſame Rank</hi> in which they ſtand, it may be to the <hi>whole Church</hi> of which they are.</p>
            <p>But they who take ſuch a lawleſs Liberty as this, may make any thing out of any thing, and transform the beautifulleſt pieces of Religion into black and bloughty Prophaneneſs. Thus the Eternal Son of GOD, for aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Divinity, was arraign'd of Blaſphemy, <hi>Matt.</hi> 26.65. And for working Miracles by the Power of the HOLY
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45821:12"/> GHOST, was decry'd for a Conjurer; the <hi>Jews</hi> averring openly to his Face, that <hi>He caſt out Devils by</hi> Beelzebub <hi>the Prince of Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what a Multitude of wretched Aggravators are there in this Age? Such as buſily imploy their Tongues and Pens, not only in making bad things worſe (which is an ill work, and ſpeaks them very Corrupt that do it) but alſo in perverting things that are good, ſo as to make them ſeem Odious and Impious; as if they took a Pride in letting the World know they have Peſtilential Ink, or a Breath ſo Virulent, as to be able, in a manner, to blaſt Holineſs it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Forbear Reproaching.</hi> Uſe no opprobrious or diſgraceful Language; for as that proceeds from want of Temper, and aloud proclaims us to be ſharp and bitter; ſo it tends but to the Increaſe of Gaul and Acrimony: Rather obey the Apoſtle therefore, who in the cloſe of this Chapter, charges Chriſtians to <hi>put away <hi>all</hi> Bitterneſs, Clamour and evil Speaking:</hi> Let no abuſive or exaſperating Reflections be made by us, either upon thoſe in Communion with us, or upon any amongſt us or about us: <hi>Deviliſh Papiſts, Damn'd Fanaticks, Mad Diſſenters,</hi> or the like, are words that ſound ill, and ſignifie worſe; for they that <hi>ſo</hi> let fly againſt their Fellow-Chriſtians, intending baſely to brand them, do moſt ſhamefully ſtigmatize <hi>themſelves:</hi> If <hi>they</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted <hi>Carnal,</hi> and <hi>recorded</hi> for ſuch, who ſaid, <hi>I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>and I of</hi> Apollo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.4. what Character muſt <hi>they</hi> come under, who in ſpite and diſparagement to their Brethren, call them by names of a worſe Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? Certainly they forget how the Son of GOD, when His perfidious Diſciple came to betray Him, gave him no worſe Title than that of <hi>Friend.</hi> And how the Prince of the Angels conteſting with the Devil; in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45821:12"/> midſt of Altercation, durſt not bring, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Charge of Reproach</hi> againſt him.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Forbear Revenging. Dearly Beloved avenge not your ſelves,</hi> ſays the SPIRIT, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19. To do that would be daring and dangerous: For beſides that 'tis a Breach of the Goſpel-Precept, of not rendring Evil for Evil; It is moreover an Incroachment upon GOD's Right, and a bold Uſurpation of His Prerogative, who has appropriated Revenge unto Himſelf: <hi>Vengeance is mine, I will repay, ſaith the</hi> LORD. And more than once the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> calls Him, <hi>The GOD to whom Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance belongeth.</hi> Not that He has made the Work pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to Himſelf for any extraordinary <hi>Pleaſure</hi> He takes in it; but becauſe He only is <hi>able</hi> to execute it <hi>aright;</hi> in fitting Inſtances, that is, and juſt Proportions: For <hi>He</hi> only knows the Malice of Mens Hearts, and the Peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Spirits, and the ſecret Malignity of their Intentions, as well as the true Obliquity and Baſeneſs of their Actions: Which <hi>we</hi> being utterly Ignorant of, upon that account alſo muſt forbear Revenge, elſe we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take what we are unable juſtly to perform; another piece of unwarrantable Raſhneſs and Preſumption.</p>
            <p>Leaving Vengeance to GOD therefore, who alone can take it in equitable Meaſures, and with unerring Exactneſs; let us give up our ſelves to the oppoſite Duties, as the Goſpel requires, and be very Diligent and Exemplary in them. As we are inſtructed in the laſt Verſe of this Chapter, <hi>Let us be kind one to another, tender-hearted, forgiving one another, even as</hi> GOD <hi>for</hi> CHRIST's <hi>ſake hath forgiven us.</hi> And as we are taught elſewhere, <hi>If our Enemies hunger, let us feed them, if they thirſt, let us give them drink. Let us do good againſt evil, and overcome evil with good;</hi> and never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the worſt Unkindneſſes, but with Prayers and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45821:13"/> Civilities. So we ſhall conform to the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and ſignalize our ſelves by a noble Imitation of their Glorious Patterns; of whom we find it thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, <hi>Being reviled, we bleſs; being perſecuted we ſuffer it; being defamed we intreat,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.12, 13.</p>
            <p>But if the Spirit of Revenge be ſo ſtrong in any, that they cannot bridle or reſtrain it, I will ſhew them how they may beſt vent it: Let them ſeriouſly think how <hi>many</hi> Wrongs, and withall how <hi>grievous</hi> ones, they have done to GOD, their Neighbours, and their own Souls; and let their vindictive Humour run out againſt their <hi>Sins,</hi> and be ſpent upon <hi>themſelves:</hi> So they ſhall break no Unity.</p>
            <p>Which if we would not do, we muſt <hi>Forbear one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> at leaſt in the ſeveral Inſtances mentioned: For Deſpiſing Mens Failings, Cenſuring their Actions, Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating their Faults, Reproaching their Perſons, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging their Ill turns; are almoſt direct and natural Provocations to Wrath, and Strife, and Hatred, and Malice. And where-ever theſe Evils riſe and rule, there <hi>is,</hi> there <hi>can be,</hi> no room for Unity: There are and muſt be Heart-burnings and Animoſities, and they have always Jars and Diſcord in their Train. Unleſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we exerciſe <hi>mutual Forbearance</hi> in the aforeſaid Caſes, and that with all good Care and Conſcience, we plainly ſhew we are no Friends to Unity. Perhaps I might ſay, we are perfect, cruel Enemies to it, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of healing the fearful Gaſhes made in it, do ſtab it to the Heart, and add to its bleeding gaping Wounds.</p>
            <p>As to forbearing <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Impoſitions,</hi> I have ſaid nothing; that's the Concern of thoſe in Authority, and it is not the part of a Popular Diſcourſe to preſcribe to Governors: Though I cannot but think it would be matter of Joy to good Chriſtians, to ſee the Terms of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45821:13"/> Communion with any pure Church made as <hi>few</hi> as they may be, and thoſe few made as <hi>eaſie</hi> as they can be, by being ſtretch'd out to the utmoſt Extent, of a wiſe, and ſafe, and moſt enlarged Charity.</p>
            <p>And happy it is, where in framing and receiving of Church-Conſtitutions, favourable Indulgence and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention in the Rulers, meet with Flexibility and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diential Compliance in the People: For where the Tempers of both are ſo laudable in themſelves, and Congruous to each other, they will be ſure Foundations of a ſolid Unity: Of ſuch a Unity, as by being Pleaſing and Satisfactory in its Conditions, will be either indiſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or of laſting Duration.</p>
            <p>And here I beg leave to make one Remark upon what occurs in the Fifteenth of the <hi>Acts:</hi> In that Chapter we find the Apoſtles and Elders together holding a Council. And after ſerious and mature Debates, relating to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Gentile Converts, they came to this prudent and moderate Determination. <hi>It ſeemed good to the</hi> HOLY GHOST <hi>and to us, to lay no greater Burthen upon you, than theſe</hi> NECESSARY <hi>Things.</hi> Now <hi>that</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil being the moſt Apoſtolical that ever met, <hi>this</hi> muſt be the moſt Authentick that was ever made, and ſo the pureſt Preſident, if not perfecteſt Standard for Sacred Impoſitions, that the Catholick Church can <hi>ſhew,</hi> or <hi>go</hi> by upon Earth. And <hi>this Council,</hi> and <hi>this Canon,</hi> laying no other things upon Chriſtians, but what were <hi>Neceſſary:</hi> Hence it will follow, that if Particular Churches would draw the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>beſt Example</hi> into Practice; they muſt take the ſame Meaſures, and impoſe only ſuch things as are abſolutely <hi>Neceſſary</hi> in their own Nature, or elſe upon great and high Accounts.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45821:14"/>
            <p>And when we find in the Caſe alledged, that an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different thing, <hi>Abſtinence from things Strangled,</hi> was required as Neceſſary, to further the Aſſociation of Judaizing Chriſtians with Believing Gentiles: From hence it may be argued with Parity of Reaſon, that 'tis <hi>neceſſary</hi> Indifferent things ſhould not be impoſed, where that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition may hinder the Coaleſcence of diſſenting Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians with the impoſing Church.</p>
            <p>Yet this, on the other ſide, muſt be added: That <hi>no indifferent things impoſed,</hi> nor any thing <hi>leſs</hi> than <hi>down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Sin</hi> in the Terms of Communion with any Church, can juſtifie our Separation from that Church. And the Reaſon is evident, becauſe Separation, where it is not abſolutely needful to avoid Sin, becomes a Sin in it ſelf, by being an unlawful Breach of that Unity of the SPIRIT, which GOD hath ſo poſitively and peremptorily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned. And where Separation is thus ſinful (as it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways is, where we are not forc'd upon it to ſhun Sin) we muſt chuſe to ſubmit to any Inconveniencies, rather than be guilty of it. For it is much better that <hi>we</hi> ſhould be uneaſie, than that GOD ſhould be offended. Much better for us to be incommoded in our Circumſtances, than to be defiled in our Conſciences.</p>
            <p>Nor may we leave a Church for <hi>more Purity's ſake,</hi> in whoſe Communion we may continue <hi>without Sin.</hi> For beſides that upon this Account, we may for ever ſeparate and ſub-divide, and run out <hi>Criminous Schiſms</hi> into an endleſs Proceſs or Multiplication: We muſt be grievouſly Prepoſterous in our Procedure. What ſenſible Man would attempt to waſh his Hands white with Ink? Or go about to take a Spot from off his Face, by plunging himſelf over Head and Ears into Mire? And are not they as little rational in their Enterprize, and not only more <hi>Abſurd</hi> but <hi>Faulty</hi> too, that ſeek to advance Purity
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45821:14"/> by ſinning; and that commit a Crime, to cure an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection? And this is truly the caſe of thoſe, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from one Church in whoſe Communion they are innocent and ſafe; to ſet up another purer than that. Inſtead of bettering themſelves, they become really worſe; and well they <hi>may,</hi> and needs they <hi>muſt,</hi> becauſe <hi>they do evil that good may come,</hi> Rom. 3.8.</p>
            <p>To check Inclinations of ſeparating upon ſuch an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, it may properly be conſidered, that no Church upon Earth is, or can be <hi>compleatly Pure:</hi> Some kind of Droſſineſs cannot chuſe but be Inherent in it, as being indeed of the very Nature of it. And can it conſiſt with Reaſon, to pull a living Body to pieces, to rinſe its Bowels from ſuch an Impurity as is rather <hi>Natural</hi> than <hi>Noxious?</hi> Eſpecially if we conſider, that when all is done, <hi>Natural</hi> Feculence will <hi>ſtill</hi> be <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main <hi>inſeparable,</hi> unleſs the Body wherein it reſts, be clarified from it by ſome mighty Change. And when the Church has undergone the Change ſhe hopes for, ſhe ſhall then be a <hi>Pure</hi> Church indeed. For ſhe ſhall be <hi>Glorious, not having Spot, or Wrinkle, or any ſuch thing; but ſhall be Holy and without Blemiſh,</hi> Eph. 5.27. But this being the Privilege of her <hi>Triumphant State,</hi> it is not to be look'd for in <hi>any part</hi> of her while it is <hi>Militant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to forbearing <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> Care is taken: And I own it is my Hearts deſire, and I nothing doubt but it is Yours alſo (and even meer good Nature, without the additional Tenderneſs of Religion, cannot methinks but prompt all to wiſh it) <hi>That Penal Laws may never touch the Harmleſs, but have the Dint of their Severity turn'd upon the Obſtinate.</hi> Penal Inflictions muſt be improper to lay upon Men of good Minds, and hurtleſs Principles;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45821:15"/> that Innocently go on in wrong ways <hi>meerly</hi> becauſe they <hi>ſcruple</hi> the Right: For ſuch harſh Methods, inſtead of inward Satisfaction, the thing they want, do only give them outward Trouble. And as for honeſt well-meaning Chriſtians, who are no whit leavened with Perverſeneſs or Contumacy, and whoſe Fault lyes <hi>wholly</hi> in their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding:</hi> Poor Souls! they are Unhappy enough in erronious Conſciences, and need <hi>not</hi> be <hi>puniſh'd</hi> too be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are miſerable. Again therefore I wiſh, that all who err in Simplicity, may eſcape with Impunity; and none may ſmart for what they cannot help.</p>
            <p>Nor needs <hi>this Forbearance</hi> (which is ſuppoſed to make all <hi>Cautious Diſcrimination</hi> betwixt the Tender-conſcienc'd and others) be a Ground or Occaſion of <hi>Jealouſie</hi> to the State: For where GOD ſees it impartially exerciſed, He will find the Government ſo like his Own, that his watchful Providence will take due Care that ſuch a Lenity ſhall rather eſtabliſh, than weaken or overthrow it. And ſo I paſs to the ſixth Rule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Live in Chriſtian Love.</hi> The Church of CHRIST, in this very Chapter, is compared to an <hi>Humane Body;</hi> and elſewhere in Scripture to a <hi>Stone Building.</hi> Now as ſuch a Body muſt have <hi>Sinews</hi> to knit its Joynts, and ſuch a Building muſt have <hi>Mortar</hi> to cement its Stones: So the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> muſt have <hi>Chriſtian Love</hi> to unite its Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. And therefore the Apoſtle, for preſerving Unity, in the ſixth place, exhorts us to Amity. Yea, he gives a broad Hint, that even <hi>Toleration</hi> or <hi>Forbearance</hi> it ſelf, will no farther promote Unity, than as it <hi>proceeds</hi> from <hi>this</hi> Principle, by beſeeching us to forbear one another, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:45821:15"/>
            <p>Love is the very Life, and Soul, and Eſſence of Unity; ſo that where the one is not, the other cannot be: As there can be no Fire, where there is no Heat; and no Day where there is no Light: As there can be no Muſick where there is no Harmony; and no Beauty where there is no Symetry; ſo there can be no Unity where there is no Love. Look what the Root is to the Tree, or the Foundation to the Houſe: What the Baſis is to the Pillar, or the Center to the Circle: And the ſame is Love to Unity. It cannot be produced, it cannot be preſerved, it cannot be increaſed or perfected without it.</p>
            <p>Here then let us do our part again: Let us <hi>Love as Brethren,</hi> as we are counſel'd from on high; and <hi>let Brotherly Love continue.</hi> Let us <hi>be knit together in Love, and be rooted and grounded in Love, and walk in Love, as</hi> CHRIST <hi>hath loved us.</hi> And truly though Unity were not the Effect of this; yet who would not chuſe, and ſtudy, and ſtrive to live in Love, conſidering how delectable a thing it is? Delectable, I muſt own, beyond my Ability of deſcribing it. Only this let me ſay, It is an inexhauſtible Fountain of ſingular Pleaſure: A Spring of ſecret, but high Contentment; and a Source from whence flows the inceſſant Streams of a noble Satisfaction. There is nothing more Soft, nothing more Sweet, nothing more Generous and throughly gratifying amongſt vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Paſſions, than an exalted, refined, univerſal Love. And therefore GOD has injoyn'd it, and made it the <hi>ſecond great Commandment,</hi> like the Firſt; not only to give us matter of Duty, but to lay a Foundation of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs for us. And truly did <hi>we</hi> love all the World as our ſelves, and did <hi>they</hi> love <hi>us</hi> ſo again (according to the Tenour of the Divine Law) how could we be Happier here upon Earth, or what could raiſe us nearer to Heaven?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45821:16"/> Where, I dare confidently affirm, that the choiceſt part of the Saints Felicity, lyes in their Love to GOD, and one another.</p>
            <p>In Compliance therefore with the Holy Direction, let us <hi>be kindly affectioned one to another;</hi> and let us <hi>provoke one another to love.</hi> Let our Love be of the right kind, without Diſſimulation: And let it be of a juſt Extent, reaching to all without Exception: Only it muſt be freer and more fervent to ſome, than it is to others, according to the Grounds and Meaſures of a wiſe Diſtinction.</p>
            <p>And ſince our LORD bids us <hi>love our Enemies;</hi> that any are ſuch, muſt be no Bar to our Affections. Yea, there is reaſon enough for that Love, beſides His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: For if we be his unfeigned Diſciples, the worſt our Enemies can do us, be they never ſo bad, is but to benefit us: To give us occaſion to act our Duties, and exerciſe our Virtues, and ſo to improve our Graces here, and our Glories for ever. And have we not ſufficient reaſon to love the Inſtruments of our ſo great Good? Yea, ſhould any prove ſuch Enemies to us, as to perſecute us to the very Death, they would be but our eternal Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors: For even while they kill us, their kindly cruel Hands would help to ſet a Crown of Life upon our Heads, and a Brighter too than other Saints ſhall wear. So that indeed we ought not only to love our Enemies, but to love them for the <hi>very Injuries</hi> they think to do us; for even by them they advantage us mightily, and while they deſign us nothing but Miſchief, they do obliquely, and beyond their Intention, ſerve our beſt Intereſts.</p>
            <p>I note but one Rule more which is included in the Text, and it is this: If you would preſerve Unity, <hi>be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45821:16"/> to maintain Peace.</hi> As that helps to tye us faſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one, ſo without it we inevitably fall into Diviſions, as a Sheaf of Corn falls aſunder that has no Band. And therefore the Apoſtle, as a true Promoter of the Unity of the SPIRIT, injoyns us to keep it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the Bond of Peace.</hi> And great reaſon we have to do ſo, there being no one ſingle Duty which GOD has charged upon us more ſtrictly: For in the Holy Writings what is more forcibly recommended, more peremptorily required, more frequently and alſo more earneſtly incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated than Peace? <hi>Seek Peace and purſue it. Have Peace one with another. Be at Peace amongſt your ſelves. Follow Peace with all Men. If it be poſſible, as much as lyeth in you, live peaceably with all Men.</hi> So that it is not enough for us to accept Peace when it is offered; to embrace it when we meet it; to hold it when we have it: But when we have it not we muſt <hi>ſeek</hi> it; when it flees from us we muſt <hi>follow</hi> it; and never ſtop till we overtake it. Though the Terms be hard, yet if they be reaſonable, if they be lawful, and ſo <hi>poſſible,</hi> Our LORD commands us not to refuſe them; His Goſpel binds us to ſubmit to them, and that <hi>with all Men.</hi> Be they <hi>who</hi> they will, <hi>what</hi> they will, if they be but <hi>Men,</hi> we muſt, <hi>if poſſible,</hi> live peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably with them.</p>
            <p>And no wonder ſuch ſolemn Injunctions from Heaven, ſhould be laid upon Chriſtians to maintain Peace, when it is a thing not only tranſcendently Excellent in it ſelf, but attended with many ineſtimable Benefits: I beg leave to mention but a few of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It defends from many Sins.</hi> He that is not at Peace with his Brother, is ready to be <hi>Angry</hi> with him <hi>without a Cauſe:</hi> To revile him, and call him <hi>Racha,</hi> or <hi>Fool:</hi> To be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45821:17"/> reveng'd on him for his Overſights or petty Injuries: To quarrel him, and fight him (as the unhappy Cuſtom is) it may be to kill him; at leaſt to <hi>Hate</hi> him; whereby, in St. <hi>John</hi>'s account, he is a Murtherer though he kill him not. Peace is a good Defenſative from theſe Evils, and from many other which now I cannot reckon up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is a mighty Friend to Juſtice. Then had thy Peace been as a River, and thy Righteouſneſs as the Waves of the Sea,</hi> ſays the Prophet, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 48.18. Where Peace flows as a River, there Righteouſneſs ſwells like an Ocean. But if the River of Peace be dried or damn'd up, the Sea of Juſtice will be at a low Ebb.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It fits us for the Enjoyment of GOD's propitious Preſence. Live in Peace, and the GOD of Love and Peace ſhall be with you,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11. But He that ſuffered not <hi>David</hi> to build Him a Temple, becauſe he was a Man of Blood; will never make them Temples for Himſelf to reſide in, that are not Children of Peace. For GOD's ſake therefore live in Peace, that ſo ye may be Happy in the Fruition of his Preſence.</p>
            <p>I might go on and add, it is an Help to Duty; a Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard to Truth; a Furtherance of Love; the Fewel of Joy, a Support of Order; an Encouragement of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Arts and Sciences; the thing which Seaſons and Sweetens all Accommodations, and crowns the higheſt Proſperity with Happineſs. But I give only one Hint more of its Worth.</p>
            <p>It is a main piece of our future Recompence, and a Branch of the Eternal Worlds Felicity: <hi>To every Man that worketh good, there ſhall be Glory, Honour and Peace,</hi> Rom. 2.10.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45821:17"/> Not only a peaceful <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> but a peaceful <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> above. As there ſhall be no Difference there betwixt GOD and Man, by reaſon of a perfect Reconcilement; and no Feuds betwixt a Man and Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by reaſon of abſolute Contentment: So there ſhall be no Diſcord betwixt one Man and another; by reaſon of a thorough Compoſure of all things, and an entire Pacification on all ſides, fixing the whole Body of Bleſſed ones in a ſweet Agreement. As our Sins ſhall there be turned into Innocence, our Corruptions into Holineſs, our Sorrows into Joys, and our Troubles into Triumphs: So all our various Enmities and Diſſentions ſhall exſpire into endleſs Peace and Quietneſs. O then let us in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure live <hi>now,</hi> as we ſhall do <hi>hereafter:</hi> Live here upon Earth for one ſhort Moment, as we muſt do in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Regions for ever; if at laſt we be worthy to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit them.</p>
            <p>I now conclude with one Direction, which if well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, will conduce effectually, to the ſettling of an Happy Peace amongſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us be ſincerely Religious. The Wiſdom that is from above, is first Pure, and then Peaceable,</hi> James 3.17. And where this Wiſdom, which is true Religion, prevails in us, and gets the Aſcendent over all evil Principles, it will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Impregnate us with its own noble Properties; making us not only <hi>Pure</hi> in our <hi>Nature,</hi> but <hi>pacifick</hi> in our <hi>Temper.</hi> And nothing indeed can be more powerful either to procure or eſtabliſh Peace, than true Religion. For the truly Religious mortifie their Luſts (from whence come Wars and Strifes amongſt us, both Naturally and Judicially at once,) they ſubdue their Paſſions, bridle their Tongues, bear Affronts, ſuffer Injuries, ſhun Debates,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45821:18"/> obey Magiſtrates, ſubmit to Miniſters, hate Diviſions, love Concord, offend none, oblige all: So that would every one of us be ſincere Chriſtians, no farther Care need be taken for Peace: It would as certainly be the Reſult or Product of our Religion, as it is the Law and end of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And as true Religion would make for Peace (verifying its Character of <hi>first Pure and then Peaceable</hi>) ſo GOD would ſee that Peace ſhould be the Effect or Conſequent of it. <hi>When a Mans ways pleaſe the</hi> LORD, <hi>He maketh even his Enemies to be at Peace with him,</hi> Prov. 16.7. So that were our ways ſincerely Religious, and pleaſing to the LORD, Peace and we ſhould quickly meet, and after that ſhould never part; our very Enemies would be unable to raviſh it from us. Then it would not matter in the leaſt, how Numerous, Malicious, Potent, Politick, Furious, Implacable, our Adverſaries are, or at any time prove; for they ſhould all be at Peace with us: If they would not <hi>chuſe</hi> to be ſo, GOD would <hi>make</hi> them to be ſo; and would ſome way or other bind them <hi>to</hi> the Peace, and bind us up <hi>in</hi> it.</p>
            <p>And when once we are bound up in the Bond of Peace, how faſt ſhall we ſtand in the Unity of the SPIRIT, and how ſecurely ſhall we <hi>keep</hi> it? Provided, that is, that we always <hi>endeavour</hi> it. And as it behoves us all to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>diligently</hi> and <hi>ſtrenuouſly endeavouring</hi> to keep it by <hi>all</hi> good Means: So <hi>particularly</hi> by the Uſe of <hi>thoſe</hi> good Rules now delivered: Which as I <hi>dare</hi> not, ſo You <hi>muſt</hi> not call <hi>my</hi> Rules: For though I have opened and urged them; yet, as has been noted, they are the Rules of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſo the Divine Rules of GOD Himſelf: Of that GOD <hi>Who maketh Men to be of one Mind in an
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45821:18"/> Houſe.</hi> Of that GOD who beſt knows by what Rules and Means to make the whole Chriſtian Church be as once it was; <hi>of one Heart and one Soul,</hi> Acts 4.32.</p>
            <p>Which that it may be, let us humbly implore it at the hands of GOD: Let us make it a daily Petition in our <hi>private</hi> Devotions: And as often as we can, let us joyn with the Church in her <hi>Publick Prayers,</hi> and ſupplicate for Unity with becoming Earneſtneſs: Where ſhe prays, in the <hi>Litany, That it may pleaſe</hi> GOD <hi>to give to all Nations <hi>Vnity,</hi> Peace and Concord:</hi> And in the <hi>Collect for all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Men,</hi> That <hi>all who profeſs and call themſelves Chriſtians, may be led into the way of Truth, and hold the Faith in <hi>Vnity</hi> of Spirit, in the Bond of Peace, and in Righteouſneſs of Life:</hi> And in the <hi>Prayer for the Church-Militant,</hi> That GOD <hi>would inſpire continually the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church with the Spirit of Truth, <hi>Vnity</hi> and Concord; and grant that all they that do confeſs his Holy Name, may agree in the Truth of his Holy Word, and live in <hi>Vnity</hi> and Godly Love.</hi> Where our Church, I ſay, prays thus for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> let us humbly and heartily joyn in the <hi>Petitions,</hi> pouring them out with an elevated Zeal, and the higheſt Streins of a moſt intenſe and vehement Fervency.</p>
            <p>And at preſent let us beg the invaluable Bleſſing, in part of that <hi>Collect,</hi> which is the <hi>laſt ſave one,</hi> in the <hi>Office</hi> for the late ſolemn <hi>Monthly Fast:</hi> Which I could wiſh all Holy Supplicants, that are Lovers of Unity, would <hi>conſtantly</hi> uſe in their devout Retirements and Addreſſes to Heaven; till ſuch time as they either compoſe or meet with a more pregnant Form.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:45821:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> GOD the Father of our LORD JESUS CHRIST, our only SAVIOUR the Prince of Peace, look down in much Pity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion upon this Church and Nation. Give us Grace ſeriouſly to lay to Heart the great Dangers we are in by our unhappy Diviſions. Take away all Hatred and Prejudice, and whatſoever elſe may hinder us from Godly Union and Concord: That as there is but one Body, and one SPIRIT, and one hope of our Calling, one LORD, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one GOD and Father of us all: So we may henceforth be all of one Heart, and of one Soul, united in one Holy Bond of Truth and Peace, of Faith and Charity, and may with one Mind, and one Mouth Glorifie Thee O GOD, through JESUS CHRIST our LORD. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45821:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
